The first time
أول مرة
I felt fear
شعرت فيها بالخوف
I was 41 years old.
كان عمري 41 عامًا.
People have always said I was brave.
كان الناس يقولون دائمًا أنني شجاعة.
When I was little, I'd climb the highest tree,
عندما كنت طفلة، كنت أتسلّق أعلى شجرة،
and I'd approach any animal fearlessly.
وكنت أقترب من أي حيوان دون خوف.
I liked challenges.
أحببت التحديات.
My father used to say,
اعتاد أبي أن يقول:
"Good steel can withstand any temperature."
"الصُلب الجيد يمكنه أن يتحمّل جميع درجات الحرارة."
And when I entered into Colombian politics,
و عندما انخرطت في السياسة الكولومبية،
I thought I'd be able to withstand any temperature.
اعتقدت أني سأكون قادرة على احتمال أي درجة حرارة.
I wanted to end corruption;
أردت القضاء على الفساد؛
I wanted to cut ties between politicians and drug traffickers.
أردت قطع العلاقات بين السياسيين وتجّار المخدرات.
The first time I was elected,
أول مرة تم انتخابي فيها،
it was because I called out, by name,
كان بسبب أنني هاجمت -بالاسم-
corrupt and untouchable politicians.
السياسيين الفاسدين الذين لا يمكن المساس بهم
I also called out the president
وهاجمت الرئيس أيضًا
for his ties to the cartels.
لعلاقته بالعصابات.
That's when the threats started.
عندها بدأت التهديدات.
I had to send my very young children out of the country one morning,
واضطررت إلى إرسال أطفالي الصغار خارج البلاد صبيحة يوم ما،
hidden, all the way to the airport, in the French ambassador's armored car.
مختبئين طوال الطريق إلى المطار في سيارة السفير الفرنسي المصفّحة.
Days later,
بعدها بأيام،
I was the victim of an attack, but emerged unharmed.
تعرّضت لهجوم ولكني خرجت سالمة.
The following year,
وفي السنة التالية،
the Colombian people elected me with the highest number of votes.
انتخبني الكولومبيون بأكبر عدد من الأصوات.
I thought people applauded me because I was brave.
ظننت أن الناس يشيدون بي لأنني كنت شجاعة.
I, too, thought I was brave.
وأنا أيضًا ظننت أنني شجاعة.
But I wasn't.
ولكنني لم أكن كذلك.
I had simply never before experienced
لأني ببساطة لم أكن قد اختَبَرت أبدًا قبلها
true fear.
الخوف الحقيقي.
That changed
ذلك تغيّر
on February 23, 2002.
في 23 فبراير 2002.
At the time, I was a presidential candidate in Colombia
في ذلك الوقت كنت مرشحة للرئاسة في كولومبيا
promoting my campaign agenda,
أروّج لأهداف حملتي الانتخابية،
when I was detained by a group of armed men.
عندما اعتقلتني مجموعة مسلحة من الرجال
They were wearing uniforms with military garments.
كانوا يرتدون أزياء عسكرية موحّدة.
I looked at their boots; they were rubber.
ونظرتُ إلى أحذيتهم؛ كانت من المطاط.
And I knew
وكنت أعلم
that the Colombian army wore leather boots.
أنه وفي الجيش الكولومبي يلبسون أحذية جلدية.
I knew that these were FARC guerrillas.
فأدركت أنهم فدائيون تابعون للقوات المسلّحة الثورية الكولومبية (فارك).
From that point on, everything happened very quickly.
ومنذ تلك اللحظة، حدث كل شيء بسرعة.
The commando leader ordered us to stop the vehicle.
أمر قائدهم بإيقاف السيارة.
Meanwhile, one of his men stepped on an antipersonnel mine
في الوقت نفسه داس أحد رجاله على لغم مضاد للأفراد
and flew through the air.
وطار في الهواء.
He landed, sitting upright,
ووقع، جالسًا باعتدال
right in front of me.
أمامي مباشرة.
We made eye contact
تلاقت أعيننا
and it was then that the young man understood:
وعندها فهم ذاك الشاب
his rubber boot with his leg still in it
أن حذاءه المطاطي وساقه التي ما زالت بداخله
had landed far away.
قد سقطا بعيدًا.
(Sighs)
(تنهّد)
He started
بدأ
screaming like crazy.
يصرخ كالمجنون.
And the truth is,
وفي الحقيقة،
I felt -- as I feel right now, because I'm reliving these emotions --
شعرت كما أشعر الآن، تنتابني هذه المشاعر مرة أخرى
I felt at that moment that something inside of me was breaking
شعرت في تلك اللحظة بأن شيئًا في داخلي كان يتحطّم
and that I was being infected with his fear.
وبأن خوفه قد أصابني.
My mind went blank and couldn't think;
أصبح عقلي فارغًا ولم أستطع التفكير؛
it was paralyzed.
كان مشلولاً.
When I finally reacted,
عندما أبديت أخيرًا ردّ فعل،
I said to myself,
قلت لنفسي،
"They're going to kill me,
"سيقتلونني،
and I didn't say goodbye to my children."
ولم أودّع أطفالي."
As they took me into the deepest depths of the jungle,
وبينما أخذوني إلى أعمق أعماق الغابة،
the FARC soldiers announced
أعلن جنود فارك
that if the government didn't negotiate,
أنه في حال لم تتفاوض الحكومة،
they'd kill me.
سيقتلونني.
And I knew
وكنت متيقنة
that the government wouldn't negotiate.
أن الحكومة لن تتفاوض.
From that point on,
ومنذ تلك اللحظة
I went to sleep in fear every night --
وأنا أذهب إلى النوم خائفة كل ليلة...
cold sweats,
عَرَق بارد،
shaking,
ورعشة
stomach ache,
وألم بطن
insomnia.
وأرق.
But worse than that was what was happening to my mind,
ولكن الأسوأ من هذا كله هو ما كان يحدث لعقلي،
because my memory was being erased: all the phone numbers,
لأن ذاكرتي كانت تُمحى: جميع أرقام الهواتف
addresses,
والعناوين
names of very dear people,
وأسماء المُقرّبين إليّ
even significant life events.
وحتى أحداث الحياة المهمّة.
And so,
بسبب ذلك،
I began to doubt myself, to doubt my mental health.
بدأت أشكك في نفسي، أشكك في صحتي العقلية.
And with doubt came desperation,
ومع الشك أتى اليأس،
and with desperation came depression.
ومع اليأس أتى الاكتئاب.
I was suffering notorious behavioral changes
كنت أعاني من تغييرات سلوكية
and it wasn't just paranoia in moments of panic.
ولم يكن الأمر جنون الارتياب في لحظات الفزع فحسب؛
It was distrust,
بل كان فقدان الثقة
it was hatred,
والكُره
and it was also the urge to kill.
وكان أيضًا الشعور برغبة في القتل؛
This, I realized
هذا ما أدركته
when they had me chained by the neck to a tree.
عندما قيّدوني من عنقي إلى شجرة.
They kept me outside that day,
تركوني في الخارج ذلك اليوم،
during a tropical downpour.
خلال أمطار استوائية غزيرة.
I remember feeling an urgent need to use the bathroom.
أتذكر أني شعرت بحاجة ماسة لاستخدام الحمام.
"Whatever you have to do,
"أيًا كان ما تودين فعله،
you'll do in front of me,
ستفعلينه أمامي،
bitch,"
ياعاهرة."
the guard screamed at me.
صرخ الحارس بتلك الجملة في وجهي.
And I
وأنا
decided at that moment
قررت تلك اللحظة
to kill him.
أن أقتله.
And for days,
ولأيام،
I was planning, trying to find the right moment, the right way to do it,
كنت أخطط محاوِلة إيجاد اللحظة المناسبة والطريقة المناسبة لفعلها،
filled with hatred,
مشحونة بالكره،
filled with fear.
مشحونة بالخوف.
Then suddenly,
وفجأة،
I rose up,
استيقظت،
snapped out of it
أفقت من هذا،
and thought:
وفكرت:
"I'm not going to become one of them.
"لن أصبح واحدة منهم.
I'm not going to become an assassin.
لن أصبح قاتلة.
I still have enough freedom
ما زلت أملك حرية كافية
to decide
لأقرر
who I want to be."
مَن أود أن أكون."
That's when I learned that fear
تعلمت حينها أن الخوف
brought me face to face with myself.
قد وضعني في مواجهة مع نفسي.
It forced me
أجبرني
to align my energies,
على تنظيم طاقاتي،
to align my meridians.
وتنظيم مساراتها في جسمي.
I learned that facing fear
تعلّمت أن مواجهة الخوف
could become a pathway to growth.
قد تكون طريقًا للنموّ.
A lot of emotions arise when I talk about all of this,
مشاعر كثيرة تتدفّق بينما أتحدث عن كل هذا
but when I think back,
ولكن عندما أعود بذاكرتي،
I'm able to identify
فأنا قادرة على تعريف
the steps I took to do it.
الخطوات التي اتخذتها لفعل ذلك.
I want to share three of them with you.
أريد أن أشارككم ثلاثة منهم.
The first
الأولى
was to be guided by principles.
كانت التوجه حسب المبادئ.
Because I realized
لأنني أدركت
that in the midst of panic and mental block,
أنه في منتصف الفزع وانغلاق الذهن
if I followed my principles,
إذا اتبعت مبادئي،
I acted correctly.
فسأتصرّف على نحو صحيح.
I remember the first night
أتذكر الليلة الأولى
in a concentration camp that the guerrillas had built
في معسكر الاعتقال الذي بناه الفدائيون
in the middle of the jungle,
في وسط الغابة،
with 12-foot-high bars,
بقضبان يصل طولها 12 قدمًا،
barbed wire,
وبأسلاك شائكة،
lookouts in the four corners
وأبراج مراقبة على الأربع زوايا،
and armed men pointing guns at us 24 hours a day.
ورجال مسلحين يوجهون أسلحتهم نحونا طوال 24 ساعة في اليوم.
That morning, the first morning,
ذلك الصباح، صباح أول يوم،
some men arrived, yelling:
وصل بعض الرجال؛ يصرخون:
"Count off! Count off!"
"قوموا بالعدّ! قوموا بالعدّ!"
My fellow hostages woke up, startled,
استيقظ الرهائن الآخرون، مفزوعين،
and began to identify themselves in numbered sequence.
وبدأوا بتعريف أنفسهم بترتيب رقمي.
But when it was my turn,
ولكن عندما جاء دوري
I said,
قلت:
"Ingrid Betancourt.
"إنجريد بيتانكورت.
If you want to know if I'm here, call me by my name."
إذا أردتم معرفة ما إذا كنت هنا فادعوني باسمي."
The guards' fury
غَضَبُ الحراسِ
was nothing compared to that of the other hostages,
لم يكن يُقارَن بغضب الرهائن الآخرين؛
because, obviously they were scared --
لأنه من الواضح أنهم كانوا مرعوبين...
we were all scared --
كنا مرعوبين جميعًا...
and they were afraid that, because of me, they would be punished.
وخشوا أن يُعَاقَبوا بسببي.
But for me,
ولكن بالنسبة لي،
beyond fear was the need to defend my identity,
الأهمّ من الخوف كان الحاجة لأن أدافع عن هويّتي،
to not let them turn me into a thing or a number.
لكيلا أسمح لهم بتحويلي إلى شيء أو رقم.
That was one of the principles:
هذه واحدة من المبادئ:
to defend
الدفاع
what I considered to be human dignity.
عما أعتبره جزءًا من كرامة الإنسان.
But make no mistake:
ولكن لا تخطئوا:
the guerrillas had it all
العصابة كانت تملك كل شيء
very well analyzed --
حللوها تحليل جيدًا...
they had been kidnapping for years,
كانوا يخطفون منذ سنوات،
and they had developed a technique
وقد طوّروا أسلوبًا
to break us,
لكسرنا،
to defeat us, to divide us.
ليهزمونا، ليفرّقونا.
And so,
وبناءً على ذلك،
the second step
فالخطوة الثانية
was to learn how to build supportive trust,
كانت تعلّم كيفية بناء ثقة داعمة،
to learn how to unite.
لنتعلّم كيف نتّحد.
The jungle is like a different planet.
الغابة تشبه كوكبًا آخر.
It's a world
عالم
of shadows, of rain,
من الظلال، والأمطار
with the hum of millions of bugs --
مع طنين الملايين من الحشرات...
majiña ants, bullet ants.
نمل الأمازون ونمل الرصاص.
I didn't stop scratching a single day while I was in the jungle.
لم أتوقف عن الحك يومًا واحدًا عندما كنت في الغابة
And of course, there were tarantulas, scorpions, anacondas ...
وبالطبع، كان هنالك عناكب وعقارب وأفاعي...
I once came face to face with a 24-foot long anaconda
مرة من المرات واجهت أفعى بطول 24 قدما
that could have swallowed me in one bite.
يمكنها أن تبلعني بقضمة واحدة.
Jaguars ...
الفهود...
But I want to tell you
ولكن أريد إخباركم
that none of these animals did us as much harm
بأن لا أحد من هذه الحيوانات سبب لنا أذية
as the human beings.
أشدّ من البشر.
The guerrillas terrorized us.
أرهبتنا العصابة.
They spread rumors.
نشروا الإشاعات.
Among the hostages, they sparked betrayals,
بين الرهائن، أثاروا الخيانات
jealousy,
والغيرة
resentment,
والامتعاض
mistrust.
والريبة.
The first time I escaped for a long time was with Lucho.
أول مرة هربت فيها لمدة طويلة كانت مع لوتشو.
Lucho had been a hostage for two years longer than I had.
كان لوتشو رهينًا أقدم مني بسنتين
We decided to tie ourselves up
قررنا ربط أنفسنا
with ropes
بالأحبال
to have the strength to lower ourselves into that dark water
لنحظى بالقوة وندني أنفسنا في المياه المظلمة
full of piranhas and alligators.
المليئة بسمك البيرانا والتماسيح.
What we did was, during the day, we would hide in the mangroves.
مافعلناه كان، خلال النهار، اختبئنا في أشجار المانغروف.
And at night,
وفي الليل،
we would leave, get in the water,
نذهب إلى المياه
and we would swim and let the current carry us.
ونسبح وندع الرياح تحملنا.
That went on for several days.
استمر هذا لعدة أيام.
But Lucho
ولكن لوتشو
became sick.
أصابه المرض،
He was diabetic,
كان يعاني من مرض السكر،
and he fell into a diabetic coma.
وسقط في غيبوبة سكر.
So the guerrillas captured us.
وبذلك قبضت علينا العصابات.
But after having lived through that with Lucho,
ولكن بعد معايشة ذلك مع لوتشو،
after having faced fear together, united,
بعد مواجهة الخوف سوية، متحدين،
not punishment, not violence -- nothing --
لا العقاب ولا العنف...لاشيء
could ever again divide us.
يمكنه أن يفرق بيننا.
What's certain is,
المؤكد هو،
all the guerrillas' manipulation was so damaging to us
أن جميع تلاعب العصابات كان مدمرًا لنا
that even today,
لدرجة أنه إلى اليوم،
among some of the hostages
بين البعض من الرهائن
from back then,
من ذلك الوقت،
tensions linger,
طالت حدة التوترات بينهم،
passed down from all that poison
ناقلين كل ذلك السم
that the guerrillas created.
الذي صنعته العصابات.
The third step
الخطوة الثالثة
is very important to me,
هامة بالنسبة لي
and it's a gift that I want to give to you.
وهي هدية أرغب في منحها لكم.
The third step is to learn how to develop faith.
الخطوة الثالثة هي تعلم كيف تنمّي إيمانك.
I want to explain it like this:
أريد أن أشرحها هكذا:
Jhon Frank Pinchao
جون فرانك بينشاو
was a police officer
كان ضابط شرطة
who had been a hostage for more than eight years.
ورهينًا لأكثر من 8 سنوات.
He was famous for being the biggest scaredy-cat of us all.
كان مشهورًا بكونه أكبر قط جبان من بيننا
But Pincho -- I called him "Pincho" --
ولكن بينتشو...أسميه "بينتشو"
Pincho decided that he wanted to escape.
قرر بينتشو الهروب.
And he asked me to help him.
وطلب مني مساعدته.
By that point, I basically had a master's degree in escape attempts.
في ذلك الوقت، حظيت بدرجة الماستر في محاولات الهرب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So
بعد ذلك
we got started but we had a delay,
بدأنا ولكن أجلنا الأمر،
because first, Pincho had to learn how to swim.
لأنه أولًا، كان على بينتشو تعلّم السباحة.
And we had to carry out all these preparations in total secrecy.
وكان علينا إنجاز جميع هذه التجهيزات في سرية تامة.
Anyway, when we finally had everything ready,
على أي حال، عندما جهزنا كل شيء،
Pincho came up to me one afternoon and said,
قدم بينتشو إلي في أحد الأيام وقال،
"Ingrid, suppose I'm in the jungle,
"إنجريد، افترضي أنني في غابة،
and I go around and around in circles, and I can't find the way out.
وأدور في دوائر لا يمكنني الخروج منها
What do I do?"
ماذا علي أن أفعل؟"
"Pincho,
"بينتشو،
you grab a phone,
تمسك هاتفًا،
and you call the man upstairs."
وتتصل بمن هو في الأعلى"
"Ingrid, you know I don't believe in God."
"إنجريد، تعلمين بأنني لا أؤمن بالرب."
"God doesn't care. He'll still help you."
"الرب لايهتم بذلك. سيساعدك "
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It rained all night that night.
استمر المطر طوال الليل تلك الليلة
The following morning,
وفي الصباح التالي،
the camp woke up to a big commotion,
استيقظ المعسكر على ضجة كبيرة
because Pincho had fled.
لأن بينتشو هرب.
They made us dismantle the camp, and we started marching.
جعلونا نهدم المعسكر، وبدأنا في المشي.
During the march,
خلال المشي،
the head guerrillas told us that Pincho had died,
أخبرنا رئيس العصابة بأن بينتشو مات،
and that they had found his remains
وبأنهم وجدوا بقاياه
eaten by an anaconda.
أكلته أفعى.
Seventeen days passed --
انقضت 17 يومًا...
and believe me, I counted them, because they were torture for me.
وصدقوني، قمت بعدّهم لأنهم كانوا تعذيبًا لي
But on the seventeenth day,
ولكن في اليوم السابع عشر،
the news exploded from the radio:
انفجرت الأخبار من الراديو:
Pincho was free and obviously alive.
بينتشو كان حرًا وعلى قيد الحياة.
And this was the first thing he said:
وكان هذا أول ما قاله:
"I know my fellow hostages are listening.
"أعلم بأن زملائي الرهائن يسمعون.
Ingrid,
إنجريد،
I did what you told me.
فعلت ماقلتِه.
I called the man upstairs,
اتصلت بمن هو في الأعلى
and he sent me the patrol that rescued me from the jungle."
وأرسل لي دورية أنقذتني من الغابة."
That was an extraordinary moment,
كانت تلك لحظة مذهلة،
because ...
لأن...
obviously fear is contagious.
من الواضح بأن الخوف مُعدي.
But faith is, too.
ولكن الإيمان أيضًا معدي
Faith isn't rational or emotional.
الإيمان ليس عشوائيا أو عاطفيا.
Faith
الإيمان
is an exercise of the will.
تطبيق للمشيئة.
It's the discipline of the will.
هو من ضوابط المشيئة.
It's what allows us to transform everything that we are --
إنه ما يسمح لنا بتحويل كل ما نحن عليه...
our weaknesses, our frailties,
ضعفنا ووهننا،
into strength, into power.
إلى قوة وصلابة.
It's truly a transformation.
إنه تحوّل بحق.
It's what gives us the strength
إنه ما يعطينا القوة
to stand up
لنقف
in the face of fear
في وجه الخوف
look above it,
وننظر فوقه،
and see beyond it.
ونرى ما بعده.
I hope you remember that,
أتمنى أن تتذكروا هذا،
because I know we all need
لأنني أعلم بأننا نحتاج جميعًا
to connect with that strength we have inside of us
لأن نتصل بتلك القوة التي نملكها داخلنا
for the times when there's a storm raging around our boat.
عند الأوقات حينما تعصف الرياح بمركبنا.
Many, many, many, many years passed
مضت العديد والعديد والعديد من السنوات
before I could return to my house.
قبل أن أعود إلى منزلي.
But when they took us, handcuffed, into the helicopter
ولكن عندما أخذونا، مكبلين، إلى الهيلكوبتر
that finally took us out of the jungle,
التي أخذتنا أخيرًا خارج الغابة،
everything happened as quickly as when they kidnapped me.
حدث كل شيء بنفس سرعة خطفي.
In an instant,
في لحظة،
I saw the guerrilla commander at my feet,
رأيت قائد العصابة عندقدمي،
gagged,
مكمم الفم،
and the rescue leader,
وقائد الإنقاذ،
yelling:
يصرخ:
"We're the Colombian army!
"نحن الجيش الكولومبي!
You are free!"
أنتم أحرار!"
The shriek
الصراخ
that came out of all of us
الذي أطلقناه جميعًا
when we regained our freedom,
عندما استعدنا حريتنا،
continues to vibrate in me to this day.
ما زال يتردد داخلي إلى هذا اليوم.
Now,
الآن،
I know they can divide all of us,
أعلم بأنه يمكنهم التفريق بيننا جميعًا،
they can manipulate us all with fear.
يمكنهم التلاعب بنا جميعًا بالتخويف.
The "No" vote on the peace referendum in Colombia;
رفض استفتاء السلام في كولومبيا،
Brexit;
خروج بريطانيا،
the idea of a wall between Mexico and the United States;
فكرة الجدار بين المكسيك والولايات المتحدة،
Islamic terrorism --
الإرهاب الإسلامي...
they're all examples of using fear politically
هذه كلها أمثلة على استغلال الخوف سياسيًا
to divide and recruit us.
لتفريقنا وتجنيدنا.
We all feel fear.
جميعنا نشعر بالخوف.
But we can all avoid being recruited
ولكن يمكننا جميعًا تجنّب تجنيدنا
using the resources we have -- our principles, unity, faith.
باستخدام المصادر التي نملكها...مبادئنا ووحدتنا وإيماننا.
Yes, fear is part of the human condition,
نعم، الخوف هو جزء من حالات الإنسان،
as well as being necessary for survival.
مثل الحاجة إلى النجاة.
But above all,
ولكن فوق هذا كله،
it's the guide by which each of us builds
القائمة التي يبنيها كل أحد منّا
our identity, our personality.
هويتنا، شخصيتنا.
It's true, I was 41 years old the first time I felt fear,
صحيح، عندما كان عمري 41 سنة وأول مرة أشعر فيها بالخوف،
and feeling fear was not my decision.
والشعور بالخوف ليس قراري.
But it was my decision what to do with that fear.
ولكن ما أفعله بذلك الخوف هو قراري.
You can survive
يمكنكم النجاة
crawling along, fearful.
بالزحف خائفين.
But you can also
ولكن يمكنكم أيضًا
rise above the fear,
تجاوز الخوف،
rise up, spread your wings,
انهض وافرد جناحيك،
and soar, fly high, high, high, high, until you reach the stars,
وحلق عاليًا حتى تصل النجوم،
where all of us want to go.
إلى حيث نودّ جميعًا الذهاب.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)